Contact

joan.bourne@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/joan-bourne (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Basic Life Support (BLS) Mental Health Nursing

Joan Bourne RN, BSN, CMSRN

Registered Nurse (RN) | Licensed Clinical Social Worker (LCSW) | VETS2INDUSTRY volunteer

Atlanta, Georgia

Summary

Certified Medical Surgical Registered Nurse with 2+ years acute care experience and a background as a Licensed Clinical Social Worker (LCSW) highly skilled in crisis intervention and counseling. Bachelor's of Science in Nursing (BSN), accepted into the Doctor of Nursing (DNP) - Psychiatric Mental Health Nurse Practitioner (PMHNP) at Maryville University with an anticipated graduation of May 2024. Demonstrated passion for working with children and the military community.

Experience

VETS2INDUSTRY

Military Spouse and Dependent Advocate (Volunteer) September 2019 - Present (10 months)

Assist Military Spouses and Dependent Children in identifying and accessing resources.

Bayhealth

Registered Nurse

September 2017 - May 2020 (2 years 9 months)

Dover, Delaware

- Prioritizes and delegates patient care activities based on patient assessment and using the five rights of delegation.
- Provides patient care based on practice guidelines, standards of care, and federal/state laws and regulations.
- Assesses and evaluates patient care needs and applies critical thinking skills in patient care management.
- Maintains strong communication with patients, families, physicians, and staff to improve patient outcomes.
- Makes recommendations to Nurse Manager to improve unit functionality and patient experience.

• Serves as Charge Nurse, managing a 20 bed ortho/neuro/spine unit.

Delaware Guidance Services for Children and Youth, Inc. Crisis Counselor July 2018 - August 2019 (1 year 2 months)

Dover, Delaware Area

- Evaluated, diagnosed, and provided therapy for children and adolescents identified as high risk for suicide.
- Provided consultation and support to schools and families with children and adolescents at high risk for suicide.
- Collaborated with Mental Health facilities to reduce the rates of hospitalization of low to moderate risk children and adolescents.
- Conducted research and utilized evidence based practices such as Dialectical Behavior Therapy (DBT), motivational interviewing, and Trauma Focused Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (TF-CBT).

Exceptional Therapies
Outpatient Therapist
December 2015 - December 2017 (2 years 1 month)
Dover, Delaware

- Complete comprehensive bio psycho social assessments and evaluation of children, adolescents and adults in the military and civilian community.
- Develop, implement, and revises individualized treatment plans to maximize patient outcomes.
- Documented assessments and therapeutic progress in accordance with organizational policies and procedures.
- Remained current within advances in the field of social work through, workshops, seminars and conferences.

Delaware Guidance Services for Children and Youth, Inc. Crisis Counselor/ Project Safety Counelor March 2012 - March 2016 (4 years 1 month)

Dover, Delaware Area

- Completed Crisis Risk Assessments of children and adolescents experiencing an acute mental health crisis.
- Provided consultation and support to parents, schools, hospitals, child welfare workers and law enforcement.
- Utilized knowledge of community resources in planning for the treatment of patients experiencing mental or behavioral health crises.

- Attended specialized training in Dialectical Behavioral Therapy (DBT),
 Motivational Interviewing, and Trauma Focused Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (TFCBT).
- Completed year long Supervisor Training Program.

NBN

Case Manager

May 2011 - February 2012 (10 months)

- Supervised the provision of services by a team of 10-15 Behavioral Interventionists.
- Collaborated with the Delaware Division of Prevention & Behavioral Health Services to ensure continuity of care to children/adolescents with a qualifying behavioral health diagnosis.
- Performed case management activities of assessment, problem identification, treatment planning, coordination of care, and ongoing monitoring and evaluation of client progress.
- Reviewed and submitted service authorizations, billing and payroll.

Southwest Human Development

Family Reunification Counselor

June 2010 - November 2010 (6 months)

- Safely expedited the return of children in out-of-home placement back to the family home.
- Aided in the stabilization and safe maintenance of the child in relative/kinship, adoptive homes, or back in the family home.
- Created individualized treatment plans, provided counseling to both the child and the family, and intervened in the case of an acute crisis.
- Educated parents on effective behavior management, stress management, and self-care.
- Collaborated with community agencies to ensure needs of the child and family were met.

United States Air Force

Mental Health Counselor

August 2009 - May 2010 (10 months)

- Performed mental health evaluations and treatment for active duty, reserve, and retirees.
- Provide social work services various settings including mental health, substance abuse, and family advocacy.
- Provided consultation during high risk for violence team meeting.

 Conducted research regarding military members perceptions and utilization of mental health services.

Washington Elementary School District School Social Worker January 2009 - May 2009 (5 months)

- Facilitate workshops and other learning opportunities for students, families and teachers
- Run individual and group counseling sessions utilizing research based social and emotional practices
- Educate stakeholders on child development and hos it affects student performance and behavior
- Create and foster a positive learning environment
- Observe refugee students in the classroom and provide education and consultation to teachers regarding cultural considerations and overcoming barriers to student success
- Establish and maintain strong lines of communication with parents of at risk students

Southwest Human Development Family Support Specialist January 2007 - January 2009 (2 years 1 month)

- Provided prenatal education for a healthy pregnancy
- Educated parents on preparing a home for their new baby
- Shared fun, creative, hands-on ways to bond with baby
- Connected families to community resources
- Supported families in utilizing effective stress management and self-care activities
- Completed developmental assessments (ASQ & ASQ-SE) and referred children for further evaluation if needed

ValueOptions, Inc.®

Case Manager

July 2006 - January 2007 (7 months)

- Outreach and tracking of assigned clients with a designation of severely mentally ill.
- Conducted independent assessments and annual re-assessments of assigned case load.
- Developed a comprehensive case plan to address areas of risk and/or need, updated plan as indicated

- Provided continuity of care through field and telephonic outreach, psycho education, crisis intervention, and referral for further services as appropriate.
- Collaborated with client's medical/health and community based providers regarding client's treatment/discharge needs and plan of care.

Education

Maryville University of Saint Louis

Doctor of Nursing Practice - DNP, Psychiatric Mental Health Nurse Practitioner - PMHNP · (2020 - 2024)

Wilmington University

Bachelor of Science - BS, Nursing Practice · (2018 - 2019)

Delaware Technical Community College

Associate's Degree in Nursing, Registered Nursing/Registered

Nurse · (2015 - 2017)

Arizona State University

Masters, Social Work · (2007 - 2010)